Singing the Traparian of Pascar, Christ is risen from the dead,
trampling down death by death, and upon those in the tombs
be stowing life. During the pastoral season,
and extending to Pentecost, we do not pray,
O heavenly King, the Comforter, the Spirit of truth,
because the Comforter comes at Pentecost.
That is the hardest one. I am so used to O heavenly King,
Comforter, the Spirit of Truth, throughout every...
And now we re-
replace it with Christ as risen. Three times. Christ is risen. Three times. Christ is risen.
Christ is risen. May you and yours have a wonderful, blessed, bright,
pastoral season. Indeed, he is risen. The 153 is a regular podcast of the Antiochian Archdiocese
Department of Missions and Evangelism. You may contact the department at 153 at ancient faith.com.
That's the numbers 153.
at ancientfaith.com.
This has been a listener-supported presentation
of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancientfaithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous
with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations
and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down
worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with...
it well. How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live Colin show focused on enchantment
in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout
history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits. Christ is risen, He truly is risen good evening. You are
our listening to the Lord of Spirit.
podcast. My co-host father, Stephen D. Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am father and your Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania. And if you're listening to
us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855-237-2346.
Montes Coutruri is taking your calls tonight, which we will get to in the second part of our show.
So the word blessing is probably one of the most nebulous religious terms of our time. People say,
God bless you when you sneeze and
And Christ in celebrities showing off their wealth do so with hashtag blessed.
A lot of the time the word blessings just seems to mean good stuff.
What about cursing?
Is that just bad juju?
So what exactly is a blessing or a curse?
Are these just religious sounding synonyms for good or bad things?
What does it mean when God blesses or curses?
What does it mean when the scriptures tell us to bless God?
How does that even work?
To the blessings and curse.
of human beings actually do anything, is this some kind of Christian magic. So this is what we're
talking about tonight, and does this mean that especially since its allergy season here in Eastern
Pennsylvania, this is the one episode where I'm allowed to sneeze on the air. What do you think,
Father? Yes, but oh, we're only allowed to sneeze twice in a row. Oh, okay. If you see that
Third time or more you're milking it and just trying to draw attention to yourself
And we have to have a discussion about humility.
There are people who, and I'm not one of them, but there are people who have like, a huge
number of successive sneezes in a row, bam, bam, you know, like, I don't know.
But it is a thing.
Well, I'm not talking about that woman on that's incredible.
Right.
Where with John Davidson and Pran Tarkin, then.
Wow.
Who sneezed for like seven years straight or something.
I mean, there are outliers.
Our first 80s pop.
a reference for the night. But your average, your average local parishioner,
does not need the sneeze more than twice in a row. And if they really do, they could
politely excuse themselves. Okay. Well, you know, maybe I should have
technical difficulties tonight. That'd be different. Yeah. Sorry, Father, I'm just
having to go to the difficulties. Why goes and sneezes because of the pollen.
So, all right, well, we are talking about blessings.
So we're not starting with,
this.
this is though this time, or Chitalhoic, right?
But Deuteronomy.
I mean, not that we couldn't.
We are going to hit up Ugarit later on in the episode.
As one does.
Yeah.
But yeah, not right here at the beginning.
We're actually beginning at the end of the Torah.
Not the end of the Bible.
We're beginning at the end of the...
in Deuteronomy chapters 28 through 30, which most people have not read or heard publicly a whole lot.
But which everyone should hear more. And for our fellow clergy out there, it really preaches.
throwing out the time begins when God says today I lay before you life
and death, blessings and cursors, right?
Choose.
I mean, that's right.
That preaching.
You can work with that.
I think that would be good for a wedding sermon.
Yeah.
Right?
Baptism.
Yeah.
Exactly.
But so there's sort of a hackneyed way this gets read
or sort of shortened when it is read.
and then there's sort of a deeper way.
And hopefully we're gonna,
we'll start out with this sort of hackneyed way,
right?
We'll go a little deeper.
So the hackneyed way is basically,
if you obey the commandments,
good stuff will happen to you.
And if you disobey the commandments,
bad stuff will happen to you.
Yeah, I mean, this is a narrative
you see all over the Bible.
Well, yeah, or at least this sort of hackney version.
I mean, yeah, right.
This is Joe's friends, right?
Yes, right.
Yeah, right.
I'm going to say, hey, all this bad stuff happened to you.
You must have done something awful, man, to deserve all this.
Yeah, right, right.
So is it like that tower that fell on people?
Where was that?
It said, you know, you suppose that these are all worse sinners than everyone else in
that city because the tower fell on them.
Yeah.
I once knew a man who preached on that text the Sunday after 9-11 happened.
that's in you sir.
Our bowl.
Wow, not recommended.
Wow.
Right.
Yeah.
And so that is a way.
And I say it's a hackneyed way.
But you will find some very sophisticated biblical interpreters
basically taking that skim on the old testament.
Right.
Let's say that's how the old testament works.
If you do good stuff, good stuff happens to you.
if you do bad stuff, bad stuff happens.
happens to you. This is basically the secret, right? You put good stuff out into the world and good stuff comes back to you, right? Yeah.
And bad stuff and bad stuff. But that's not really what's going on, right? In due to our enemy. Right, because bad things do happen to good people and good things happen to bad people.
Yes, this is the impulse on the righteous and the other.
Yeah, that's not just a new revelation.
in the New Testament, right?
Yeah.
The aforementioned Book of Job, right?
So we sort of ended up last time talking
about the sense in which the commandments of Scripture
have life in them, right?
And what that means, right?
that it's by actually doing, right, by putting this...
interpreters into practice, right?
That we find sort of life and abundance.
And this is the sense in which we see the blessings
of the covenant, right?
The blessings which come for keeping the commandments, right?
Which come in relation to keeping the commandments,
is in this sense, right?
That the commandments have life in them.
And then the opposite, then,
is what we find.
in the curses. So that curse is sort of if a blessing is life, a curse is like anti-life.
It's the opposite. So death, corruption, all of these things.
And we see this in sort of one of the, I mean, these are always, we're not going to read all three chapters, but when you read these, right?
One of the main contests we're dealing with in a
gray in society, so people are farming.
And so in the forefront of the blessings is,
you know, the rain will come in its season,
the ground will be fertile for your crops, right?
Things will grow, there will be life, right?
In that sense.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's why people often read this as if you do good things
then good things happen to you, because like this,
That is a reading, it's a very flat reading.
but it is like that those connections are being made.
But that having a life in good order sort of produces
then life, right?
Yeah, right.
And so then that's contrasted in the curses with
this curse situation of the sky being like iron
and the ground being like bronze.
Yeah, just great writing a great first.
So forming, not working.
Yeah, it's black and gray.
sky, right?
Ron's got nothing's growing out of it.
No rains coming from it.
And so that is the way in which death and corruption
sort of spiral from bad order, right, or false order.
It's not a complete descent into chaos,
but there's actually a sort of negative order
or an evil order, a tyrannical order,
Yeah, wait.
Yeah, right. Yeah. And that kind of order does not produce life and produce this corruption and death and produces the opposite. Yeah. Right. And so these are the two.
These are the two sets of images, right, that are set up here. And you can see from that example, we just gave about the crops and the sky and the ground. Right.
But this has to do with the relationship between
humans and the cosmos, right, the world, the universe, the creation. Right. Right.
This is about how humans live in creation and that human activity in creation, then bringing
about either this abundance of life or this sort of corruption, this sort of anti-life
corruption. Yeah, I mean, which just connects back to the mission that God gives.
Adam and even Genesis, you know, to fill the earth and to cultivate it.
That's the task so they can either cultivate it well or they can mess it up.
But either way, humans are going to affect the world.
Right. Right.
And so the good order that humans can produce is an order that's in harmony with
the order of the cosmos as God created it.
Right, and that's what.
found in keeping the commandments.
This is a way to live in the world
which is harmonious with the order
which God put into the world.
Yeah.
And therefore, it's conducive of life.
And then of course, the opposite is true, right?
When human activity operates against the order
which God has put into creation,
it's destructive both of humanity
and of the rest of the created order.
Yeah, because around you.
person. Man is not an island. Right. And so later on in the scriptures, when it talks about the
curse of the law, it's talking about Deuteronomy 29 and 30. Because the law here is the Torah, the curse
of the Torah. Yeah. Yeah. This is it here at the end, right? The curse of the Torah, which have come
come upon humanity through humanity not keeping the commandments right.
And these are actual consequences.
Right? Well, everything's fine from our perspective,
but God is really mad.
Yeah, it's not like we've been declared guilty
because it's an actual existential harm that's being done.
Living against the way that the Torah says you should live
actually does hurt you and it does hurt the world.
It's like you said, it's not just God being...
that you broke his rules that don't actually do anything or connect anything.
Right. Right. It's that this is this is produce the state of corruption and death
in ourselves and in the world around us. Right. Who are, are wickedness and are evil activity.
And so a person who is in this state of curse, right, is a person who is then alienated.
Right from...
from the rest of the creation, from his community, from his family, from himself, from God, right, because all of those things represent at least a potential harmony.
And so when our actions are at disharmony, we alienate ourselves from all of those things.
Yeah.
And so we talked before about how everything in creation is connected in this web of relationships, right, and that's what sort of gives it its identity.
Right, and so when that
that web of relationships is fractured and that harmony is broken, right? Things become
twisted and become other than what they are. Right? And so that part of what we're talking
about when we're talking about blessing is blessing over against that cursed state.
And so, blessing always involves a certain level of reconciliation, of reconnection.
those points of alienation have taken place.
Yeah, putting things back in order.
Right, because blessing is when that web of relationship is affirmed, right, it is
tightened when everything is working.
This is closely related to the idea we've talked about of justice.
Yeah, right.
Where we talked about justice is sort of everything in the right place and working correctly.
Right.
Whereas blessing occurs, focus is not so much on the overarching order, but on that web
of relationships.
makes it up the constitutes it.
The constitutes the bigger overall order.
Yeah, so it's about harmony, not just order itself.
It's about the harmony of the order
or the harmony is connected to the order.
Right.
Yeah, that makes it up the constitutes it.
Yeah.
So it's like looking at, you know,
looking at a salt crystal versus
would be like talking about justice
about justice and looking at assault molecule would be like.
talking about blessing and cursing
and this web of relationships that make up the crystal
when they're in the proper, right,
in the proper portions of connected proper.
Gotcha.
Yeah, so I imagine that one question
that some people might have would be,
is this the same thing as natural law, right?
There's this whole natural law tradition,
particularly in Western Christianity.
I mean, we don't need to go too deep into it,
but I'm-
I imagine probably some people are just thinking,
okay, is that exactly what we're talking about?
No.
Okay.
Yeah.
So,
we,
I, you know, I said, I said something nice about Thomas
who coined his last time.
I guess he, no.
This isn't really,
he's it.
But so, before the natural law concept
is really a product of Western Christianity.
right because it's come back.
to previous concepts. Okay. One of those concepts is the idea of divine law. Okay.
Which really arises in the West as such. We've talked about this before about St.
Jerome's translation of using the word Blacks.
Yeah, right
And so the idea of God
then as law giver, as promulgating laws. That was combined with Aristotle's idea of natural
right. Okay, so explain that. Yeah, that comes out of the Udemy and Ethics. And Aristotle's idea of
natural right is basically that there's an order in the world and the cosmos. That order he sees
primarily but that exclusive.
being teleological, being what things are aimed at, the purpose.
Everything has a purpose.
And everything has a purpose.
Everything has sort of a mature form.
Everything has, right.
So the acorn is growing into the oak tree, right?
There's sort of an aim and a goal and a purpose for everything
that all of those taken together constitute a harmony.
And therefore,
For any given thing, right, but we'll use humans, right?
So for a human, right?
There is this tell us, this end, this mature form of a human,
of what a human could be.
And therefore anything that a human does,
which aims at that and is conducive to that,
is sort of naturally right.
in the right thing.
to do, right? Anything which pulls you away from that then is wrong. Got you.
Right. So you could see how when you take that and the idea of God is law-giver, you get
natural law. Right. You get the idea that the law is sort of written into the nature of
things. Okay. Right. But what we're talking about is not identical with but more like what
that Aristotle was talking about.
That's a...
in that there is this correct relationship
based on the nature of any given thing.
God created the nature of everything
that's about creating human nature, right?
And human nature has qualities to it, right?
And therefore, since it has quality,
those qualities can be excellent.
it or they can be deficient. Right, right. So, you know, a chair can be good at holding
and supporting people or bad at it. And based on that you say it's a good share or a bad
share. And how well it fulfills its role. Right. And so the same thing is kind of true
with humanity. Human nature, of course, has this special destiny in God that we'll be
talking about as we continue to
night, right? So we're a little
different than the
or even then an animal, but the idea there is sort of the same, that humanity, a human
person is created to become something. And therefore, the path that leads there is sort
with the Blessed Path, the correctly ordered path.
Right.
And so before we get more into blessing,
it sort of develop out more what we were just saying.
We've got to do a little ground clearing
and a little bit of deconstruction on,
as you mentioned in your intro,
some of the ways in which the term blessing and blessing
gets used in our modern
culture, not so much the sneezing thing. We'll leave that alone for now.
Yeah, I remember that.
Hashtag blessed.
Yeah.
Other ways.
Next next time someone says God bless you to me after I sneeze.
I though I think I'm going to say hashtag blessed.
You do that.
They'll grow.
I will.
They'll move on with their lives.
They'll be okay.
But it'll be a minor but slightly amusing joke.
Yes.
Okay.
So, yeah, so blessings gets used a lot by some of our friends who have
wittingly or unwittingly desiringly or unawaridly fallen into the prosperity gospel trap.
Yes, come out from them.
So Ed, this includes more, I mean there's a gross form of this that we've all seen, right?
Yeah.
A person who shall not be named because he is deceased and it would be mean to pick on him.
Once on TVN, he had one of the greatest sermons of all time about the forehorsement of the
He said that.
He had had a vision and seen the forehorses of the apocalypse and the the crisis return was there and
The forehorses of the apocalypse are getting ready to ride out in this vision and they were they were they were
Chomping at the bit to ride out the forehorses of the apocalypse and their their hooves were churning at the ground
Returned at the ground and heaven
Heaven with the streets of gold
And as they're churning at the
the ground there and heaven in the streets of goal. Flakes of that goal were falling down from
and landing in the checking accounts of people who donated to TPN.
I mean, this is a thing though. I mean, some of these preachers, like, they'll have these
glitter bombs up in the rafters, you know, that are gold dust or whatever. You know,
miraculous gold. I mean, we're not, we're not making this stuff up.
No. So that's the gross version, right?
Yes. Right. And we could all look at that and say, like, what? Right?
Right.
There are more subtle way more subtle.
versions of this though.
Yes.
Right.
Where people kind of are like Job's friends.
And so if someone is well to do successful at the moment
then hey, they must be doing everything right.
They must be holy people.
Right.
They must be moral people.
Mark's of election as it were.
Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
And the opposite is true.
Right if they fall in unheard.
times, it must be because they're lazy or whatever, whatever, whatever.
And this is not a new thing.
This is not an American thing.
This has been going on forever because St. John Chrysostom
choose his people out about doing this, about judging the poor.
So this has been a constant thing.
And this is essentially what this boils down to the whole problem
that it equates blessings with stuff.
Yeah.
Right.
It used to be money, right?
Lessings with money.
Now that we're late, late stage capitalism, it's stuff, John.
Right.
So I can't count my blessings, name them one by one.
You could hypothetically, but if it's a list of like objects you own in your house, then
I might, yeah, I might have a start over.
Yeah.
Start your list over.
So, uh...
Yeah, so blessing is it's stuff blessing being say blessing is is is a relational category as we were just saying it's a state
In which you are
blessedness
Right you're in a state of blessedness right or
Or you are a person which
Do it wants to say but
And you shouldn't go around saying and not a popular hashtag
Yeah, hashtag a napamit
Yeah. So yeah, you don't want to say that. But yeah, because the generally the people who
are in that state don't don't necessarily realize it or don't want to admit it. But so then
what is the relationship with stuff? Because there is, right, there is this sort of it's not
really attention but people will call an attention in the Bible where they'll point at
in the Old Testament like Abraham or Job who are described as having sort of all this well,
right? It's sort of a mark of their favor with God. And at the same time, you get to the New
Testament, and Jesus doesn't say a lot of nice things about rich people. No. Other than, you know,
give all your money to the poor and become one of my disciples, right? And so people will just
Street.
that as attention or what have you where they'll say,
well, that's the difference between the old and the new
testament.
The old testament blessings were material and now
they're spiritual or something like that.
Yeah, sort of quasi-Marcy and I kind of think.
That's how you escape being in the prosperity,
gospel, you say, oh, it's just about spiritual blessings now.
Yeah.
But so there's kind of a chicken and an egg issue here.
So.
The problem is that the one side says well, you've gotten stuff therefore you're blessed
right right
Whereas
What we're talking about is no you're blessed you're living a life
Keeping the commandments of Christ you're living a life in harmony with God and your neighbor and your family and your community, right and because of that
There's life that's happening
Right and sometimes that life includes stuff
Right, but
Life does not consist of stuff no
And so right the Lord give it if the Lord take it away blessed be the name of the Lord right
That's right
right the
Stuff will can come and go
Right, but as long as you're you're living in that harmonious state. This is part of what the book of Job is about
whether they come or they go, the stuff, that harmony remains.
That state of blessedness remains.
And you can lose all your stuff and still be living in harmony with God and His creation
and your fellow human beings.
And then you're not cursed.
Right, or you can have all this stuff and be alienated from God and alienated from your family.
and alienated from your community and from the world, the natural world, and sit in your
palace of stuff all alone and be cursed.
And it's interesting as technology and everything progresses in our contemporary world, it gets
less and less hard for people to imagine how someone with all this
could be lonely and alienated and miserable?
Sure, I mean, just think about people
with a psychological problem of being hoarders.
They are surrounded with their stuff
and yet they're destroying their relationships.
They're destroying their lives.
They got plenty of stuff way more than they ever could use.
That's all rotting on their shelves.
But, you know.
Or even the celebrity, the rich guy.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Exactly.
So yeah, so this is, and these bad understandings of what blessings are and what blessing is.
What are the places where you really see the rub of that is that the sort of historic
Christian understanding of asceticism makes no sense with it.
Yeah.
Give everything up.
Why would you do that?
the most pleasant
person should be the person with the most stuff. And yet like in Orthodox tradition,
some of our, most of our highest, highest saints were people who were utterly
impoverished from the world's point of view. And in many cases gave it all up very voluntarily.
Yeah. Yeah. But even, even, I mean, this isn't just, you know, I'm going to briefly defend our
Protestant Prince here.
There are certain levels of types of asceticism that got jettisoned pretty fast, right?
I mean, old Luther went married and unbut if you look at for example, you know, the reformed traditions, right?
The Calvinist traditions, right?
They were very strongly against the spending of money.
Yeah, right you were to work hard right and having success
that's in your hard work with seeing as a mark of God's favor, even a mark of election,
right?
In the Calvinist understanding.
Right.
But people who went out and profligately spent money on clothes, on houses, on cars, on
right, that kind of thing, right, were that was taken to be the opposite.
That was taken to be a mark of that prophecy was needed to be a mark of repurpation, right?
Right.
You did not do that and that is a type of a
Yeah, sure, of course.
If you have a million dollars in the bank,
but you're driving a 30-year-old car
and you own one suit that you wear to church on Sunday,
that's a kind of a set-as-ism.
Yeah.
That gets practiced.
But so it's not just like,
oh, Protestants don't get a set-as-ism.
But if you go even in reform circles today,
for example, you don't find as much of that as you used to.
You used it.
Like in the United States, for example, even the places where there was that kind of,
and you find it, I mean, Baptist groups in the United States, right?
You don't drink, you don't smoke, you don't, right?
There were certain...
Don't smoke, drink, or chew, or date girls that do.
Yeah, yeah, if you're gonna...
You absolutely have to dance at gunpoint.
You leave room for the Holy Spirit in between you and your partner.
Right.
So
But it's all true folks, it's all true.
All of that is going away now.
Yeah, right.
And it's even getting like in the United States.
I mean, it's mostly been bleached out of Roman Catholic life.
Right.
Fasting during lens even.
Right. And and it's working on it in the Orthodox Church too.
like no one's immune to this and it's because
fundamentally, again, good old late-stage capitalism,
or experiencing now, as sort of reduce
what a human person is to just a desiring thing.
Yeah.
There's the bundle of desires.
Right, which works it into.
Yeah, which works its way out in numerous ways.
It's not just about stuff, right?
Yeah.
Like the great, like what is, I'm about to say what is love
and then everyone's going bleep.
He's not hurt.
Right.
You know, but what is love considered to be, right?
It's considered to be authentic desire.
You know, that's what it comes down to.
Like, do I really desire this person?
Do I really want them?
Do I really want to be with them?
You know, and do I meet my needs?
Right.
And of course, I mean, the emotional needs or whatever other needs.
And this is part of what's behind so much of the...
confusion about gender identities and
deviant sexuality and all of this stuff is,
as you say, it's based on this idea that human beings are basically just desires.
Then the key is to correctly identify your desires.
And once you've correctly identified them, then go be that.
Well, they go consume that.
Yeah, yeah, right.
and never ending quest to satisfy that desire.
Yeah, right. And the reason our culture has done that to human and he is it serves the ends because
once you're just a bunch of desires and consumption is the answer to those desires, then you can be
marketed to. That's what the entire advertising industry has done now for 75 years is find
ways to take whatever their product is and tap into some desire appears and tell you that it will
will be fulfilled.
And this isn't, again, this isn't something that just affects one political side or one political group, right?
There's sort of a lie that's told on both sides of the US at least political spectrum, right?
On the conservative side of liberalism, the lie is everyone can be rich.
Right, and then once you're rich you'll have all your desires met but all it does is it takes this hard work
You just go and you work
card and you'll be rich too, right? And that's a lie because Starbucks needs thousands
and thousands of hourly baristas and they only need one CEO.
Right. It's just so. Yeah. Yeah. Or as I got flayed one time because I actually said in
a sermon, every kid cannot grow up to be president. We've had 40 some and we have hundreds of
millions of people. I guess just not.
It's not the math doesn't work out. It just doesn't work.
Right, so that's the answer at the end of the travel. Just work hard
Hard enough long enough do all the right things
You two will be wealthy and then once you're wealthy you'll be able to satisfy all your desires that you can't satisfy now
Because you haven't worked hard enough for long enough yet. Yeah, and then
The flip side the progressive side of liberalism the lie is that everyone can have all of their personal desires
satisfied and they'll never conflict with each other.
Yeah, we can everyone can be completely sexually fulfilled.
Everyone can be completely personally and emotionally fulfilled.
And no one's desires will ever complete with anyone else's desire.
Yeah.
And that's that's exploded, right?
Yeah, it's yeah, it's pretty spectacularly lately.
Yeah.
Exhibit A being, you know, the sexual revolution and now meet.
to. Right. Right. So the idea that everyone could just satisfy their desires and then, oh,
wait, you can't do that without stepping on a lot of other people and consuming a lot
of other people. Yeah. So both of those are lies, right? Both of those are lies. But
you have to function with one of those lies in order to function in a system in which
you're just a ball of desires.
Right? And in a...
That's a fundamentally misshapen view of what it is to be human.
Yes.
That's reducing a human to a giant, consuming mouth.
We have images of giant mouths and Christianity.
Yes.
And the End of Caving Ball of Hell.
Yes, exactly.
It's the way to the underworld.
I mean, yeah.
Yeah.
Right.
icon here in my studio which is exactly the hell mouth.
Yeah, so we have to set aside, right?
Having seen that, that that just fundamentally doesn't work, right?
And isn't, it's not really not real, because it's not real, it's not what the scriptures
tell us, right?
And it's not what the church teaches us, right?
So the person who has their desire, desires fulfilled is not the blessed person.
the person who has their desires denied is not the person.
That's not at all right even though that's how many of us have been brought up through it in the culture and even church culture to think.
So getting back to what we were saying in the introduction to this first half and going into the terms that are used for for blessing in the scriptures.
The Hebrew word, the verb is Barack to bless. The noun form of that is Baruch, which is a name,
given name often, right, the Old Testament. That means the blessed one, the one who is blessed. But
Barack, the sort of root original meaning of it is actually to kneel.
Huh.
So
So this makes a lot of sense.
What do you think about the phrase,
bless the Lord, bless Yahweh?
That would be the neal before the Lord.
Yeah, I think a lot of times when we see it say,
bless the Lord, usually we have the sense of blessing
as something that a higher person does
towards a lower person.
And so when we hear the bless stuff,
yeah, exactly.
You mean, bless the Lord.
I'm like, well, what does the Lord need from me?
I don't have any stuff to offer here.
you
and it's not stuff.
It's not stuff.
So, but that gets a little trickier
than kneeling thing.
It gets a little trickier when we talk about God blessing you.
Yes.
Right?
Because that doesn't mean God kneeling before you.
Right.
It means more like God kneeling you.
Yeah.
Right.
If you think about, this is not, by the way,
we're not trying to portray God as general sod.
I know that's what many of you are thinking.
That's dumb.
where we're going.
You'll be for you.
Sorry.
Our second, yeah, is our second 1980s pop culture reference, at least, that I'm aware of for
these.
So if you think about kneeling in a quite literal sense, right, kneeling is changing your
posture or your orientation.
Hmm. Right. You are changing your posture.
If you bless the Lord and bless Yahweh,
you are changing your posture,
your orientation toward God.
Yeah.
And if God blesses you, if God kneels you,
he's changing your posture or orientation toward him.
Yeah, it's like the difference between retiring
and being retired.
Yes.
In short, yes.
He produced the same result.
Yes.
Exactly.
He produced the same result,
but one has done to you and the other you do yourself.
Yeah, and ideally they're both happening right?
Right ideally they're both happening and this is true not only when we talk about us blessing God or God blessing us is human
But when we in the church bless objects, right? I know we've said this before on the show
But you know you bless holy water. You're not making it magic water to kill vampires, right?
And you're not making a material component for a third level clerkspell you are
You're taking water and you're returning it to the correct orientation within the world, right?
You're returning it to where it belongs and that web of relationships we are talking about.
Right? In the world. Right. Whatever it may have been used for before that. Right?
Now it is going back to, we've talked before about, you know, the difference between the
the challenge and my Rath of Con collectors cup.
Right.
Not the material.
It's...
It's the use of the purpose, right?
The way it fits into that web of relationships, right?
Yeah.
And blessing houses the same idea, right?
It's about putting things back into the correct orientation and relinking them, right?
Reconciling them within the web of relationships that makes up the order of creation.
So the Greek word.
Yes, also slightly surprising.
Yes, it is.
It's also, it is really interesting to nerds like me at least because before it's used to translate the old testament,
this word is not to our knowledge used in explicitly religious context.
Yeah, so yeah, the word is Eveloyia, right?
which hey, let's do a little etymology.
And there's a little baby Eleanor once again.
Yeah, so I'll be right.
Evo-Logia is that beginning of, or EU,
Epsilon, Epsilon, which means good, right?
Or true.
And then, you know, Logia is from logos word.
So it literally means a good word.
but that's not how it...
You know that it just doesn't just simply mean good word right in the ancient world.
And actually, actually, I'm actually, Louis can also mean action.
Oh, there you go.
Yeah, that broader sense of logos.
Yeah, yeah. That's important for all of you,
Papias fans out there.
when he talks about St. Matthew having written down the loyah of Christ that doesn't just mean the words.
So get out of town with your cute theory.
Anyway.
Wow, throwing shade in a very specific set of people.
Yeah, I went out a little rabbit trail there, but now we're back.
Right, right. So okay, so what does it actually mean in usage in the ancient world, especially prior to
to the Bible.
Right.
it basically meant two indoors.
Yeah, so sort of cosine, right?
Two.
Right.
Which, which, okay.
So, I mean, that lends us to all kinds of fun stuff.
Like, you know, our modern English word,
eulogy, comes from this, quite directly, right?
Eveloyia.
Yeah.
Which, I mean, I'm just imagining now, you know,
someone knowing this etymology,
who's about to preach a sermon at a funeral.
and saying, you know, I will now give the endorsement
of this person who lies to you before us.
But I mean, it is kind of correct, right?
You're commending that person to God,
which is, I mean, what is that?
That's an endorsement, right?
Yeah.
And you can ask somebody to put in a good word for you.
Yes, right.
So we do have that expression in English, a good word.
And that's I think that that's the
The only, there's kind of two ways that that phrase gets used in English.
You know, to put in a good word is explicitly about an endorsement.
Then the other way that it gets used is if someone, you know, speaks a good word, which
just kind of means that they said something good to you or edifying or whatever, it might
be a blessing.
Interesting.
Yeah.
And then the other way that it gets used in the same matrix of meaning, right, is that
the word blessing is used.
in English for a sense of permission,
but it's often permission that it's almost basically
like an endorsement, right?
Like so you get a woman's father's blessing to marry her,
which is basically you're looking for his endorsement,
which people don't always get that.
They sometimes get married anyway.
So it's not just permission.
Yeah, yeah, it's not just permission.
They are looking for kind of endorsement.
And then of course we also use the word blessing
to refer much more explicit to permission and within like the Orthodox Church we say I
and you get my pre-splussing for that or my bishops blessing for that and again it's that that sense of
a word being spoken that is about again a kind of endorsement like you are blessed to do this
you know you have an endorsement to do this so so like it is in there in English we just don't
tend to think of the word blessing as meaning endorsement, right? But it's...
have all that within English so yeah yeah it is there so then the question
becomes well how do we reconcile these two ideas right we have a word that
it Hebrew means to Neil kneeling that gets translated into Greek with a word
that means to endorse right right which don't seem to have a huge bend
diagram overlap. Right? Well, so the place.
the place where these come together is this idea of harmony, right, that we were talking about
with Nealion, right, with Nealion in terms of posture and orientation being in this web of
relationships harmoniously, that if you think about endorsement, right, or favor or co-signing,
right there is always there are always two parties involved
Okay. You have one party who is doing something or who is something and then you have the other party who is co-signing that.
Right. Who is giving their agreement with that. Right. Or endorsing that or recommending that.
I mean, we use the word endorse to really refer to signing something. So like that's again, that's there in the way that we use these concepts in English.
Right. And so these two come together in the idea of divine
works, right? The divine energy is God working in creation, right? God's blessing, right,
brings you into harmony with what he's doing in the sense of adjusting your posture and
your orientation toward it. And also, right, there's that endorsement and co-signing idea,
that cooperation idea where the two are brought into alignment, right? And so that's the place
where these two ideas sort of come together.
That's right.
Uh, in terms of what's going on with blessing, right, in the scripture.
And there's a couple of other sort of phenomena within scripture regarding blessing that we
need to talk about just so we can be exhaustive and exhaust everyone.
Uh, and have, and have the first half of the show go over an hour.
Um, I'm pretty sure it's going to.
Yeah.
We're there.
Um
The first is the idea of this kind of recursive way in which blessing is used.
Right.
Blessing oneself, right, that you bless yourself.
When we use this language, you refer to making the sign of the cross sometimes.
Yeah, bless yourself.
And so, you know, for what we've just said, the idea of blessing yourself would be the idea
of bringing yourself back into a correct posture or orientation, right?
getting yourself back.
on board, right, with what God is doing, but there's one particular place where this concept
comes up that is kind of important to biblical theology.
Okay.
And by kind of important, I mean, explains polyimpiology, sorry, Calvin.
We could just say it's Genesis-level stuff.
Yes.
because it's in genocide.
And so an example of this is in Genesis 12 verse 3.
This isn't the only place this happens with regard to Abraham, but this is one of them.
So a lot of English translations of Genesis 12 verse 3 have something like,
in you will all the nations of the earth be blessed.
Right, which we did a sort of survey of almost every English translation we could find.
almost all of them said pretty much something exactly like that in you
all the nations that you were some very.
So the Hebrew is actually more like all the nations will
bless themselves in you.
Right, which is kind of a weird turn of phrase.
Right, those different translations are trying to figure
out how to render that in English.
And I would say, so if I were going to speculate,
I mean, I can't just lay out a history
of every single English translation ever made
over the last thousand years in 10 seconds.
But if I were to speculate...
as to why it tends to be, or almost always is this other way, is that the idea of blessing
yourself that concept doesn't seem to exist in most of the culture, most of the English-speaking
religious cultures that are making translations, right?
Does that, if that makes any sense, the idea that you are putting yourself into harmony
into order because there's this idea that being blast means receiving something good and so.
why would you say that the nations are going to do that to themselves? Right?
The idea is God is doing this. So so in you Abraham, God is going to do this to them, which of course
is not incorrect. Right? But that's not actually the most literal way of translating this verse.
Right. And the idea of blessing yourself with another person also is kind of odd. Yeah. Right.
right? Right. So and you'll get rearranges that the as long
kind
might not be...
surprised. The edd bible actually comes to the closest to sort of reflecting the original,
although even they punt a little because they have it as all of the nations will bless each other
in you. Yeah, and there's a try to find a way to bring out that recursive so they have
the nations blessing each other. Yeah, so the best place to understand what's going on here though
in terms of that original translation,
other than just a weird Hebrew idiom,
which is also a nice part, just say,
oh, that's a Hebrew idiom.
And see what St. Paul does with it in Abraham,
or in Romans, sorry, does with Abraham in Romans,
and this text, another related text in Romans.
And so we talked back at the beginning of this first half
about the relationship between justice and blessing.
right, blessing being about these connections in the web of relationships that make up the overall order of justice.
So, and I'm pretty sure we've talked before on the show about how justification,
the primary meaning of justification in the scripture is more like justification in Microsoft Word than like something that happens at a courthouse.
right so put straight put in order right left
justified being that's lined up on the left side right is for the right side
full and it's all around right it's all put in order. I'm always fully justified in my writing.
So you get those weird spaces in the middle of it anyway. So justification is a related
concept too. So when St. Paul wants to talk about how the nations remember Gentiles mean...
the nation. That's one of those things we translate differently in the old and new
testaments for no apparent reason. So when you talk about how the nations are justified,
how they're set right, how they're put back in order, how they're reoriented, he goes to Genesis 123.
And he goes to other related passages and says that this happens in Abraham.
Yeah.
Right.
They're just...
And...
and the way Abraham is justified.
And so St. Paul makes this theological connection
between entering the state of blessedness
and justification, right?
And he does it through Abraham
and his understanding of what's going on
in passages like Genesis 12, verse three.
Yeah.
And so this is key to sort of understanding
what he's doing and how he's...
leaving those together, what he means,
but he quotes plus this, the man who said,
so not right in a good stem, right?
And once you understand that,
then all of this sort of theoretical stuff falls away.
Yeah, it's about an actual state.
Yeah, right, right.
Okay, so what else?
Certain lawyers who became reformers.
Um.
So that reciprocal idea is not only present in this kind of idea of someone blessing themselves.
But also that as we talked about before in a ideal situation,
God is blessing us and we are blessing God.
There's this cooperation within this state of blessedness,
of blessedness or always blessed in being blessed.
And that does it again.
like everything, this isn't just an individual and God, right?
But this happens within a community, right?
So Christians as a community are blessing each other and are being blessed by each other.
We're blessing the elements of creation, right?
And we're being blessed by God and blessing God.
Right.
I mean, this is simply the...
This is, if we need to see a model for how that works, that's the life of the angels.
I mean, that's just what they're doing. They are putting things in order. They are putting,
you know, being ordered. They are, you know, all of that is happening. I mean, they're not
dealing with it in terms of sin, the way that we have to. But still, it's about, because being
put in order is not just about repairing a break. It's also about beautification, right? Which is
not necessarily about fixing something that's broken. It's, it's, you know, you can make things more
more and more beautiful by blessing the
even further, you know. Yeah. Yeah. And there's a there's a nice Greek term in Scripture for this,
this state, right, of, of blessedness, of blessing and being blessed and of the community and that's
Kenania. And those of you who studied Greek in the Anglophone world will have to occasionally
part in our Greek pronunciation of the Greek.
We're not going to say coinonia.
The Greeks would come after us.
They don't worry, live.
Right.
So we get out do that, harass me and stuff,
even if we wanted to.
But yeah, and Kenania gets translated a lot
away, Fellowship being one of the communities.
Yeah.
And Fellowship is a word that's been greatly sort of denuded
in our Western church life.
I mean when I was growing up it meant...
chicken and mashed potatoes and yeah,
cast rolls make cast rolls.
Cast rolls, yes, right?
People have it out.
That's fellowship.
Tricks of company, right?
And it's not saying that that's not part of it,
but it's much more than that, right?
So this word, keen idea that gets used in scripture
to describe this participation in communion with one another
is the same word that, for example,
Plato uses to describe the relationship between.
objects and the forms, right? Like the eternal forms, right?
The Emily plays as objects participate in, right? And that that
key to NIA, that participation makes them what they are.
Right? And so this is, again, this idea of this web of
relationships, but now within a community between people.
And again, as we've talked about before, it's those relationships.
and those
those roles and those functions as we all function together with one another that define
our identity and define who we are, right?
Not some kind of isolated individual thing.
And so then last but not least, there is another word that is translated blessed in the
New Testament.
Right.
And even in the old, if you're looking at the Greek Old Testament.
Yeah.
And that is...
Macarios. Macarios. Yeah, which is the first word in in Psalm 1. Bless us the man. We'll talk more about that a little bit later. Of course, it's a knee into right. Maccadios. Yeah, and it begins the Beatitudes.
The Beatitudes exactly. Right. And so this is the point in the program where last time it was a go. Tonight I say something nice about David Bentley heart.
See this is going to become a
and gag now too. You know, along with our whatever friends, you don't want
Father Steven to young to say something nice about you.
I'm going to say something nice about David Petley Art, and that's
specifically about his new test of a translate. Okay.
Thanks, Yale again for the review copy. Anyway,
as it was free and I'm Dutch.
But he chose to translate Macario's as blissful.
which I think is a great translation and here's why.
Because that word is used in other Greek literature to describe the life of the gods.
Yeah, right. I mean, if you pull out your Liddell and Scott Greek lexicon
that everyone should have in their shelf, right?
You can have these little...
The size, which size do you have?
Right, the little little little...
I have the middle little. I have the middle little.
So, is the little little...
I have the whole size.
I have the signs you have the great
Scott. Yes, I have the full on Oxford back with the published books. Yeah. Yeah. I have the
middle little which is pretty good. Pretty good. I mean if you look it up it literally says this
like it says like of the gods or something like that like that's that's just a dictionary definition
in the lexicon. Yeah. Yeah. So this is eating a broja right turn alive hanging out. Yeah. So
I'll be imagining those moments in Clash the Titans, you know, with all the big fake
beards.
and they're stinging around some fountain there and,
oh, Lord Zeus, you know.
Why do Greek gods have British accents
in 1960s American films?
I ask you this.
That movie was made in the 60s.
Was it? I know. Maybe you're right.
Also, it's 80s, man.
Yeah, that's right. 80s.
I'm thinking of like, you know,
Jason the Argonauts and stuff like this.
That you're, yeah, yeah.
The Ray Harryhausen stuff.
Now, there's the classic.
But, yeah.
Those are the kinds of films I was allowed to see
when I was young.
largely films that have been made 20, 30 years before.
Yeah, sort of sandal epics.
Yeah.
I don't regret a moment of it.
And you can see how that would have a, right?
So obviously that would be a blessed state.
Yes, right.
Sharing in the life of God, right?
It is a blessed state, right?
For life of the angels, as we were just talking about.
So you can see how this idea is connected to.
And why it would get translated in the same or similar ways,
Right.
But so this is one of the keys in understanding that the Beatitudes are actually about eschatology.
They're about the eternal life.
And so, especially if you look at St. Luke's version where he's got the woes,
The, you know, when he says,
blessed are you who are poor, right, that the, the, the,
person who is poor is living this divine life, right, is already experiencing eternal life.
Whereas the person who's rich, right, woe to him, he's the one who's a person, right?
And all through, there are these sort of inversions, right?
To carry across the same idea that we've been talking about through most of this half,
that we're talking about this.
We're talking about sharing in the life of God.
We're talking about communion with God.
And with your fellow creatures,
and with the creation, not about stuff.
Stuff.
Right.
All right, well, having said that,
we're gonna go ahead and take a quick break
and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855
5-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Saint Ignatius, first century bishop of Antioch,
called the God-bearer, is one of the earliest witnesses
to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child,
Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself
as an example of the ch...
like faith, all Christians must possess.
In bearing God, Father Andrew Damick recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
saint, and interprets for the modern reader five major themes in the pastoral letters
he wrote.
martyrdom, salvation and Christ, the bishop, the unity of the church, and the eucharist.
For Ignatius martyrdom is really the coolness of Christ in my sense, which that can be challenging
because number one.
He doesn't seem to have any reticence at all about going to martyrdom.
Like there's no sense of, well, this boy have to do, you know, I wish I didn't have to,
but this was God's will for me.
He is going to it joyfully, gladly.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the second half. Call in with your hashtags for blessings and curses.
We want to hear from you. So, all right, we just talked about blessings.
What's the other end? Oh, I don't want to call you out publicly or anything.
Oh, but go for it, you might as well.
Well I was just going to say that you know some folks where they have them.
popular podcast, you know, and they have commercial breaks. They would use that to
draw the attention of their audience to the works of other people.
Hey, I don't pick the commercials.
I don't, but here's the power of the, I was gonna say, if I, if I, you know,
if I told Trudy to play a commercial with one of your books, we know you run,
we, you run out of the room and we, we, you know, we can't have you do that.
You might knock something over. You might break something.
I'm happy now.
I'll just throw it.
difficulties as it is. Right. Right. So anyway, well, you know, so welcome back everybody.
Thank you for that call out. I do appreciate it. It's good to know. You know, we just gotta,
so like I said, I don't pick the commercials. There are people out there thinking about it.
So now you've been able to address the situation. Don't pick the commercials.
Just a coincidence.
Hey look it's...
It's the marketing department.
They're like, what can I tell you?
I mean, it's just the way it is.
It's not my...
There are people out there with a desire to win more.
Exactly. Ignatius.
And you're here to help me.
Exactly, exactly.
All right, so Ugratic Death Curses, right?
Yes.
Ugratic Death Curses in you.
It's the title of your next self-help book.
Yes, yes.
because you don't want any of them, you were in death
versus so we're going to actually talk about one.
I briefly thought, hey, maybe we should read it that I'm like,
nah, we should do that.
Out loud.
That's not good.
Yeah, don't we don't say those things on the air or any
ever.
I don't read out.
Yeah, don't read them out loud.
There's some guys that we're in a cabin listening.
This girlfriend would get possessed by a dead eye.
They'll all go sideways.
So we're not reading it even in a recorded format.
Exactly.
So, but in perusing the sub-huguritic death curse is not that long ago, as is my one.
I found one that I think is the original evil eye, or at least the oldest one we have,
which is reference to sort of an evil eye type of idea that we have.
And this was a curse that you would put on somebody.
And the curse is basically...
trying to attract the eye of a not, our old friend, a not.
Yeah, as in she bailed.
Sister wife of bail.
Yeah, it's master.
Father's head in, right?
If I'm murdering her correctly.
Threatened to smash her.
Threatened to.
Oh, excuse me.
If you didn't give bail a palace.
Yeah.
So,
and then I would search about and destroy them and all their stuff.
Yeah, come on.
Come on, dad slash father-in-law, give him a palace.
Yeah.
Or you'll crush your skull.
So the idea here is that these kind of curses in the ancient world
were invoking spiritual powers, right?
It wasn't that there's a person who has the whammy, right?
And could put the whammy, right?
It's not like they're asking Dan Housen to curse somebody for them.
This one.
because you're invoking a spiritual power.
Now, there were people who they would go to to put
curses on people, but those were people who are
seen to have sort of pre-existing relationships
with these spiritual powers.
Yeah.
Right.
Who are in some way already religious or magical
functionaries related to these particular spiritual beings,
who would be the ones who would do the whammy.
Right.
And so now I'm just I'm thinking suddenly of that that that game so press your luck remember that yeah, no whammy. Yeah
Wow
Actually invoking the eye of a not I had no idea
Just don't ask me to explain to you the scientific basis of the whammy
So and so these kind of curses were used in all kinds of situations right before you go to battle
you curse the other guy, right?
You know, you're commerce. You curse the rival pairs of the heart, you know, yeah, isn't this what what business what what was
Name was trying to get bail him to do to Israel like curse them so that I can beat them away. I mean yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
And we tend to think of it when it's used to the fairs of the heart. We tend to have a very
Rosie romantic view of it where it's like oh get this get my crush to fall in love with me, right?
It was usually for like...
kill my romantic rival.
That person spous so they're on the market again.
It was sort of a lot darker than that.
Yes, because clearly if you invoke a demon
to kill another person,
then they will be fine with being with you after that.
They're spouser.
They're, you know,
their mate will be happy to be with you.
Like, oh, well, you know, that's okay.
Yeah, or at least while maybe just,
they'll be too scared to that.
Yeah.
That sounds like a loving-
relationship. Yeah. So but but of course so that means that in this kind of
cursing right cursing someone is it just a question of you as a human having
ill will toward them? Nor is it just a question of some evil spiritual power
doing something to them, some align spiritual power, but there's this
participatory element, right, where a human person
is cooperating with
the civil spiritual power in order to
Bring about this this person state. Yeah, yeah, yeah
Have this happened so so having said that we actually do have someone who is called in who has a question about all of this
So Sarah are you there?
Hello Sarah welcome the Lord of spirits podcast Christ has risen
Oh, truly he is risen.
So yeah, my question I guess would be, you know, when it comes to blessing or cursing physical objects, you know, in our culture, especially popular culture, they kind of, I guess, sensationalize it.
And, you know, so in a way, I get what I'm gathering from listening is that, you know,
I'm participating in like the life of the church.
That's that's a that's a blessing.
I don't know if it makes sense, but is that kind of a blessing?
But then if you become, you know, especially, I'm a East Greek Orthodox and you know, they
like to bless objects and certain things.
And I think I've even discussed this before in the group page on Facebook, like the evil
eye type thing.
You know, and people want to have them blessed when you get baptized and things like that.
like putting too much faith I guess you could see.
in those types of objects could that make itself become a curse? Like that's what I'm curious
about. Like the objects, especially with idolatry and things like that.
Yeah, right. So, I mean, we're going to we're going to talk about this a little bit more, but I mean,
to bless an object is to put it into the correct relationship to God that it should have. I get
That's full.
My friends and stuff.
The less holy water is to make water what it truly should be.
Yeah. But then to take, it's funny you mentioned the evil eye amulets, the Mati, right, in Greek, and there's like other languages, I think it's called a Nizar, and there's various versions of this.
But if someone, I mean, think about what they're doing, right, if someone asks that that be blessed, say, with holy water, and then they use it as some kind of talisman against a curse from someone else,
not putting their faith in the cross of Christ.
not putting your face in the life of the church.
But if I have this magical thing,
because the priests put the magic on it,
then they are effectively putting it
in the other relationship.
Okay, yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah, that's effectively what's happening.
We're gonna talk more about what curses are and what they do.
But yeah, I mean, certainly people can use objects
in a cursed way.
Right? If you use them in a way that's contrary
to
God's intention for them. Does that make sense? I don't know if Father Steven, you have anything to add or correct with what I just said or?
Well, yeah, just just to add, one of the interesting things about that good old Uric Defters is not only one of the interesting things about it is that after it sort of puts the evil eye on the other person,
It then concludes with an incantation to ward off the evil eye.
the person giving the curse, right? Because there's the idea that once you enter into that world,
like it can bounce back at you, right? Or someone else can attack you with it. And so to me, the big
issue with using any kind of amulet like that against a curse like that is you're kind of entering
into that world of tit for tat, right?
Who got a little?
And uh...
That is not advisable, right?
Because what the scriptures are clear about
is that it's Christ who has defeated
all of those demonic powers.
And therefore, Ken and does protect us from them.
We don't need to try and enter in and fight.
Fire with fire, right?
Yeah, try to make over the place Christ with these,
time to object.
right. Because I'm growing up like for me growing up in the 80s when Dungeons and Dragons I was
Protestant and you know obviously everybody thought it was Satan and you know Satanic or things
like that. And I remember seeing it a youth group meeting and they were explaining to us why it
was and they said oh these objects that you play with can actually come alive. And I'm not
I can actually tell that other youths for painting.
Wow.
I am youth for.
Well.
Wow.
Luckily my parents were all sitting there.
My parents were like, boy, no.
I don't think so, but yeah.
So I find it interesting because like I said,
you see this stuff in popular culture
and it's so sensationalized that people don't think about it.
Like, oh, you know, it's like come alive in the middle of the night,
the dolls and things like that, the tax.
It's like toy story.
Totally.
Yeah, you have a toy story or a puppet mask
or anything like that.
you know, like, oh, it's a toy story to pop it, man.
So that's a lot of fun.
All right.
Well, you know, I mean, if I ever see,
so like you sometimes see the little, you know,
the blue and white eye amulets, right?
I mean, there's a really, really common, the mati.
And then especially amongst often with some at least
from people who have like a little blue beat
or a little blue stone or whatever.
And if I ever, I'll be honest,
if anyone brought one of the
those things like for a baptism because you mentioned right there we brought to
baptisms. Yeah. If anyone if anyone brought one of those things to a baptism and
they wanted you know that to be put on the child after baptism I said absolutely
not. You know you may not. That is a cross you might put an icon there that's
okay but none of that none of that amulet stuff. Oh definitely. I think that
half of that. Thank you so much. You're welcome thank you very much for calling
Sarah okay well we have one more caller that we're gonna take right now and that is
Brat, I don't know.
So now that you brought up puppet master, I think we may just want to turn the rest of the episode into a meditation on the film works of Charles band.
That's not this podcast.
Because we can segue very easily from puppet master to demonic toys.
Yeah, that would be a monologue. I mean, it'll be even yeah, it'll be a monologue on your part.
Dolman versus the demonic toy.
Yeah, yeah. No, we have Brett. Brett is waiting for us on the other line.
So, Brett, are you there?
Yes, Father's Amir.
Christ is risen.
Remember your question.
No, Father.
Yeah, barely truly is risen indeed.
That'll cover it.
That'll about cover it.
I promise Father Stephen, this question is not about furries.
Instead, my question is about how much do we need to worry about curses and
today's a
especially, particularly from, I suppose, a neopagin mindset.
I know a lot of popular idea of neopaginism
is to avoid cursing people, but you can't help
think of the popular idea of the edgy, goth-witch teenager
in the popular movie who makes a voodoo doll
put to curse on the, you know, main character,
of the, you know,
you know, forget my use of the slur, but you know,
Gipsy woman who, you know, you bump into at the supermarket
and you know, she gives you a curse.
How much do we need to worry about that
and how do we protect about it
if we do need to worry about it?
I'm gonna put that directly to Father Steven.
Okay.
He doesn't want anyone to drag him to hell, I guess.
That's what he's saying.
Or for him to get thinner.
So, man, that's a horrible...
because this half who knew. Well, you did bring up Ugaridic death curses. So that's true.
We only started getting the calls after you said that. I'm just putting that out there.
People want. I'm giving people what they want. They want Ugaridic death.
Because they're just big balls of desire for Ugaridic death.
Yes.
So, yeah, the answer is really that we, as Christians,
we don't have to worry that much.
It's not because that stuff's all hokem, right?
And we're not superstitious.
I mean, maybe a little stiches, but not superstitious.
It's, it's, it's eye of that, because that stuff is real.
Now, whether any given modern human is doing the real thing
or doing something goofy out of a book,
book they got it, parts and noble, right?
is beside the point, just in the sense that we don't have to worry about it as Christian, right?
Yeah. There is a real thing, a lot of the sort of modern stuff outside of horror movies, it's not the real thing.
It's kind of goofiness. That doesn't mean it's innocuous to the people who are dabbling in and participating.
But even if it is the real thing as Christian and this is
Several of the songs, I know we've talked about a couple of them on the show before, but
several of the songs specifically are talking about, well it's kind of sub-rosa a lot in
the English translations.
They're talking about particular like demonic powers of disease or famine or of death,
Psalm 91 or Psalm 90 in the Greek.
and sort of enumerating them.
And enumerating them in order to say,
like none of them can touch you as long as
you're blessed by the Lord in the sense
that we're talking about.
Yeah.
The, it's because we're talking about a state of blessedness
and a state of personness, right?
If you are in a state of blessedness
where you're correct.
aligned and orientated toward God and toward your neighbor, then there's nothing you have
to worry about from demonic powers. They could take your stuff. Right? Look at Joe
begin, right? But the stuff isn't the important thing as we were saying. They could even take
your help, like with Joe. They could even theoretically take your earthly life. But again, if you're
correctly oriented these other ways that isn't so.
you have to worry about because no one can harm the righteous man, right? So yeah, we shouldn't
worry about it. You shouldn't get involved in it. Friends don't let friends use witchcraft.
But, so in case I lose a bulk movies or yeah, I actually have a little story to tell related to
what you just said, Father. So if Brett will, you know, humor me for a second. So this is actually
story that my wife tells and I've heard a ton of times.
so hopefully she won't be unhappy with me passing it on.
So there was one time that she was actually out, I think with our children somewhere,
this is several years ago. And she was somewhere and in public, I get a store or something like that,
and this woman approaches her who has kind of an odd look to her. And she turns out to be some
kind of fortune teller or psychic kind of person or whatever. And she sort of made an offer to my
wife like you know
would you like blah blah blah, you know,
would you, you know, I don't remember,
I don't remember what is she offered to her.
And my wife, you know, if you were,
you guys, you know, you father Steven,
you've met my wife.
You know that she says whatever is on her mind
is to say and she says it very clearly and boldly,
you know, 99% of the time.
And she turned to this woman and she said,
we are Orthodox Christians and my husband is a priest.
And apparently the woman just sort of recoiled
and kind of ran out of the room.
Which I mean, just illustrates this, right?
Like like
You know, in the immortal words of,
I'm forgetting the name of the actress,
you know when she said to David Bowie,
you have no power over me, right?
That's, I mean, I can't think of her name, but anyway,
another 80s reference.
Are you thinking of Jennifer Connelly?
Jennifer Connelly.
That's right, Jennifer Connelly, at the end of Labyrinth,
you have no power over me.
But I mean, it's true.
It's true.
as Christians, we belong to the Lord.
know, and we're being protected by his angels and saints. So it's not a not a
huge concern. Does that helpful to you, Brett? Did we lose Brett? I think we might
have lost Brett. Well, I'm sorry to us, Brett, who did this to you?
Thank you, Father. I do appreciate it. All right. Thanks for calling in. Okay. Well
moving on, not with Ugratic Death curses, but something slightly else.
But that...
unrelated. Not unrelated. It's all related to
Ugritec death curses. So I don't recommend our t-shirt maker makes
something really. I know we've said Ugritec death curses about 12 times but
I don't recommend you put that on a t-shirt. Just put that out here.
Ugritec death curses would be kind of an awesome band to me. Yes, that is true. I have to say.
That is true.
So...
When we're talking about a state of curse, right,
and now we're going to the other side
from the state of blessed death.
So a state of curse then is this state of alienation
of being out of harmony, right,
of being out of sync,
being broken out of that web of correct relationships, right.
And that could be a human, that could be a thing, right?
Because if we say that when we bless water or a house
or whatever that we're putting it back into that.
correct level of relationships.
Right.
Then that means it can be out of it.
It can be in a state of curse.
And there are, that's talked about in the old testament
in particular, but also in the new testament,
in the ideas of impurity.
And impurity is divided into sort of two different types.
Yeah, this is a really really important
So yeah, and this is a big part of what confuses a lot of people, especially about the commandments of the Torah
And how they relate to each other is that there is moral impurity and there is ceremonial impure
Okay
And those are just categories, those aren't categories that are internal to the Bible, so don't be too much into the words or anything
It's just a way of categorizing those two things
Right. And so moral impurity up.
obviously has to do with actions, right, with actions that are taken.
Ceremonial impurity has to do with a state of uncleanness, right, that results from something
else.
So moral impurity would be a result of, say, murdering a guy, right?
as ceremonial impurity might be from using the restroom.
Right? Right. Both of those render you unclean but in different senses. Right? Like in radically different
senses. Yeah. And both of those have to be sort of taking care of those situations, have to be
taking care of. And both of those are kind of related to a state of curse. So there are differences in
degree and that kind of thing that we're going to talk about more now. But this
It causes a lot of confusion so we get, you know, it's a question that arises very naturally
when you start reading like Lebedecas, and it's like, you know, okay, well these people
are unclean because of fornication, and then these people are unclean because of, you know,
going to the bathroom or a woman's time of the month or something like this, and those don't
seem to be the same category to me.
Right, it's like it's not their fault, you know, or they were doing something they necessarily
had to do, you know, like, like, somebody's got to touch the dead body.
I mean, you can't just...
To bury it.
Yeah.
Leave it there, yeah.
And so here's sort of how this, how this sort of works out, right?
And it's part of our understanding of this state of curse, of the way that it affects
the created order, right?
So what we're talking about, what we're talking about moral impurity is we're talking
about something very much like that Ugarinic Death curse.
the sense that you have a human person.
person participating in the actions of
spiritual, evil spiritual powers. Right?
We've talked about this before, where we talked about demonization,
sort of becoming partakers, having, as St. Paul says, in
first Corinthians, Junonia with demons.
So, this kind of idea.
So what we're not talking about again.
when we talk, even though we use the word moral,
the way we think about morality now,
some people went straight to law again, right?
You did something that's against the rules, right?
That's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about something very different.
And this is how we've been talking about sin
pretty consistently on this show.
Yup.
And this comes out of the way, for example,
St. Paul uses sin in the singular to refer to this kind
of force.
out in the world and the way the fathers talk about the passions which are called passions
because they make you passive.
They act upon you and through you but render you passive.
So when you're seized by anger, the anger has control of you.
not like consciously and actively being angry, right?
less takes hold of you, pride, right?
And these are things that take hold of you.
Overcome.
Yeah.
So, and this is related to another distinction that we've talked about.
We talked about last time, we were talking about the divine energies,
this distinction in orthodox theology between God's essence and His energies.
We talked about how people and things have essences and energies too.
But this idea of energies, this idea of an area, comes out of, is sort of picked up by the
Greek fathers from a distinction that's made going back to at least Aristotle.
Where Aristotle in metaphysics, Theta, talks about this distinction between dynamism, which
would be a power strength, right? That is proper to a nature. We were talking about this a little bit earlier in this episode.
So, you know, and that's different for different types of creatures, right? So the nature of a raccoon, you know, a trash panda, has different powers than a human, right?
And then that is distinguished from energy.
or energies, which is the thing, the hypostasis, right?
The thing, the person exercising that power.
So it's not just the exercise of the power.
Right.
It is, and we've talked about this a little bit last time.
Yeah. Right.
We talked about this a little bit last time.
So it's like we talked about how, where we talk about the divine energies.
We talk about God's energies.
We're not talking about just things God does, right?
But we're talking about God doing things, right?
God loving, right?
Not just God's love, like separate from Him,
but God Himself loving.
Yeah.
And so it's when you are using your human energies,
it's you exercising the powers of your human nature, right?
And so...
All humans have the same nature, right?
We all share human nature, right?
But what distinguishes you as a person
from all the other human, you know,
seven point, whatever billion other human persons
in the world today is our particular energies,
where and when and how, at what point in space and time
and all those things, we are actually putting those various
powers of human nature that we...
all share into practice. Right. Right. Actually exercising them. Because humans don't all utilize
the same powers, right? Right. But the dynames that are the powers of sin are not part of human
nature. They're not proper to human nature has got created. Yeah, this is a really important point.
I mean a lot of the fathers, especially the the the circle
fathers talk, I mean, particularly when they're talking about the passions, right?
But they specifically say that sin is alien to us.
It is not a power of humanity to sin.
But we do sin.
So why do we, how is it that we are able to do that?
Right.
And so the demonic powers, one of the reasons they're called demonic powers, the Nameon, right,
is that when we sin, we're exercising, we're
energizing, right? We're actualizing a power that's foreign to our human nature. Yeah, it's a
power of power. Exactly. When you see in, you're using demon power. Yes. It's so scary. Scary. But
I mean, it makes so much clear, you know, when you're seeing, you're using demon power because it's not
a human power. God didn't create it. It's created us to sin. Right. And the first John,
St. John talks about Christ.
purifying the world from sin as destroying the works of the devil. Yeah. Right. That he works through
humans. Right. As he further clarifies the first chapter he talks about Cain who we're going to talk
more about in a little bit here. Right. Cain does the works of the evil one. Right. And that makes him
the son of the evil one. As we've talked about before, the son being the image of the the phob. Right.
But so because this sin, this simple Dubai power is foreign to our
Our human nature is destructive and corrupting to our human nature. Yeah, it's channeling something we're not supposed to channel
Yeah, and when we talk about curse
As a noun curse as if it were stuff right stuff that needs to be purified out
Right talking about curse ontologically, right
like you could locate it in a place or on a person. We're pointing at that corruption.
We're pointing at that rot or decay. So this is why you'll see some of the fathers saying that sin
doesn't exist. It doesn't have an ontological existence because it's just a corruption of
something that exists. So if you see an animal, a dead animal that's decaying, the decay is not
something that exists in it of itself that has been added to the animal.
Right. Right. Rather it is just a
corruption, the corruption and the
following a part of the animal. Right?
It is the lack, the lack of life, the
lack of, of wholeness, the lack of
ability of the animal. Yeah. And so
this is why it's a structure of
human nature and destructive to
through that web of relationships
and destroying that web of
relationships. It's also destructive
to the creation around us. Yeah.
Which includes...
other people, which includes other people. And this, by the way, is why repentance from an Orthodox
perspective is not just saying sorry and getting the upper-moder, okay, I won't hold that one against
you on the day of judgment. Right. It's not about guilt or innocence of a crime or getting a pass on
on a crime. Real repentance is about, is restorative. Yeah. Right. It's about.
trying to repair what we've broken and what we've destroyed and what we've corrupted and healed,
what we've damaged in ourselves and others. Right, and I mean, I was going to say, and that's why
repentance affects other people and why we even speak of repenting on behalf of other people,
is that that repair of the of the web of relationships and bringing things into right order is communal
because we're connected. We just are. Yeah. And, yeah, and reconciliation is key to the whole thing
of blessedness, taking something from...
curse to blessed is going from alienation to reconciliation.
Yeah.
And then I was going to say the, and so here's the beautiful thing.
Here's the flip side of all that nasty stuff we just mentioned.
When human beings cooperate with God, right, when we synergize with God, then we are making
use of divine energies, right?
They don't belong to us.
They're not natural to humanity.
But because they're from God, they heal and they bring us into right order.
And it's why the saints can do things that are not natural to humans
because they're making use of God's energies because they're cooperating with him.
So there's a flip side.
So this is part of what we mean when we talk about theoses
and then demonization or whatever,
because it's, again, even though they're not equal in opposite actions,
to co-op.
with the energies of God is not simply the opposite of cooperating with the energies of demons,
we can at least conceptually think of them as opposites, right? Even if existentially they're not
simply the same thing plus or minus. They're not equal opposites. Yeah, exactly. They're not equal
opposites. They're opposites, but they're not equal opposites. Yeah, and it's I think understanding
this idea of co-energizing, synergizing, co-operating.
is an understanding that we, that's not just something we can do with God, it's something
that we can do with the dark powers as well.
I think that that makes clear a lot of what it says in scripture about, you know, participating
in God's works, participating in the works of the devil and what that does to you, right?
Right.
And we're able to do that with demons because there are fellow creatures.
needed.
being that it become, that it become corrupted, right? Whereas being able, we've been made
particulars of the divine nature, are able to cooperate with the divine energies because of
Christ's incarnation. Right, because he became a creature. In the divine person of Jesus Christ,
taking on our shared human nature, he has united our shared human nature to God and made that
that place.
Yeah.
Opened up that possibility for us, which previously did not exist.
And this is why in orthodox theology, the incarnation is so critically important to salvation,
even more so than the elements that are more focused on in the West.
So all that is about what we call moral impurity.
Right.
And...
the state that state of curse that's brought about by that.
So then how is ceremonial impurity related to that?
It's not the same thing.
Right.
Why is it that some of the same words are used?
So what happens, though, is in the world we live in,
we become exposed, even if we're living
in a state of blessedness.
We become exposed to the products of sin and death.
This is why touching a corpse makes you unclear.
This is why you don't eat an animal that you find dead.
This is why bleeding makes you ceremonial, unclean.
These are things that wouldn't happen or wouldn't exist
if it worked for the presence of sin and death in the world.
Yeah, okay, so the one thing that occurs to me is that I know
that it's not obviously in this category that does make you unclean
is if you touch one of the scrolls of the Torah.
that makes you richly, ceremonially unclean.
What's going on there?
Why is that?
You know, the Torah is not the product of sin and death in the world.
Right.
Only a very roundabout way.
Yes, right.
That's right.
Right.
But, yeah, that's not why.
And this is true with other holy things too, right?
If you get the sacrificial blood on your sandal,
Right, as a, as a priest.
though it's sacrificial blood that is holy,
when it hits your shoe, your shoe now
has to go get burnt because it's unclear.
And the reason for that is that
when something is by its nature holy, right?
So once that blood becomes sacrificial blood,
or once that particular piece of vellum
or parchment.
becomes a tourist crawl, right?
It is now by nature holding.
And so if you do something that would defile that holy thing,
it kind of rebounds on it is the idea, right?
So I can't by my will, right?
Defile the sacrificial blood now that it's sacrificial blood.
And so anything I do that would defile it,
like spilling it on my shoe actually defiles my shoe.
and then back extension knee.
Got you right and so when I with my built-by center hands touch the Torah scroll
or the gospel book or whatever
I can't
Corrupt it right
I mean you could destroy it so it's no longer a Torah scroll or no longer a gospel book or no longer
Or an icon or no longer whenever it was right right
But barring that right it will remain holy and I will be the one defiled by mine
filing activity. Yeah. So, okay, well that makes sense then. So that's, that's how, that's how that
that worked. Yeah. So in, in the scriptures as a whole, not just the Old Testament because he comes
up more than people at first may realize in the New Testament, I already mentioned once in first
John, we have sort of an archetypal person, when it comes to curse, right? There's an archetypal
person one in scripture.
and that's Kane. Not Adam, we talked before about there being sort of multiple quote unquote
fall events even though that's all gotten balled up in the west into Adam.
That it's actually Kane. And while most people listening to this probably were at some kind of
POSCO service at the end of last week maybe and saw the icon.
The Anastasis, it saw Adam getting pulled up out of Hades.
You notice you don't see King getting pulled up out of Hades.
These two are different cases.
And so we see kind of that distinction made in the text of Scripture itself
in Genesis 3 and Genesis 4 when we compare them.
Adam, when he is cursed, he's told,
these told cursed is the ground because of you.
Right. Right. So be
because of what he had done.
He's now sort of alienated from the ground partially, right?
Now it's good that the ground's gonna bring
for thorns and thistles instead of food.
Sometimes.
Yeah, it's much, much harder for him to do agriculture now.
Right, so there's this level of disharmony now
between him and creation and him and his wife
and him and God, right?
That there was not before.
But when we get to Kane,
After he kills Abel, he is cursed from the ground,
where he is sort of totally alienated
from the created order, and from his family,
and from everyone else, right?
Meaning he's told the ground will not bring forth food
for him, like agriculture becomes impossible.
The sky is now like ironed in the ground like bronze,
as far as came as concerned,
because of how corrupt he has become.
And so...
It's not a coincidence that he has to find a way to live
and so he goes and he found the sick.
And from that city he founds grows as we go
across this genealogy and see his descendants come
civilization, comes technology.
And he can't live in harmony with creation.
And so this is how he has to do it.
He's gonna have to, he can't grow foods,
so he's gonna have to take food
or he's going to have to trade for food
or...
what have you right and so his alienation produces this mode of life that then further alienates his
descendants yeah right and that technology includes not only what we would call technology right
things like metallurgy and that kind of thing but also what you could call spiritual
technology all the way up through Josephus Cain is always identified as the first heritage right
he teaches his descendants to follow his ways. He's sort of a founder.
or a civilization founder figure.
And you find things like sorcery
and witchcraft and seduction
and those kind of things being created by his descendants,
which is a sort of technology to be used just for sin.
Basically, I have for the participation in these things.
And so this gets to a theme that we've talked about before
of this idea of the city.
versus the extended family that you see, like with Abraham and Lot, when Lot goes down to Sodom and Abraham lives dramatically, right?
Where rather than like with the extended family or the village kind of model we've talked about in the the blessed community
We were talking about in the first half
You now have the city as sort of the community of the alienated
Like everyone is alienated and they've all gathered there in that place
Yeah, which I mean
Think about it.
the level of that now. I mean that's even if that was true you know with Kane it's amazing
you know the sort of conglomeration of people that exists now and yet they're even more
isolated from each other because frankly because of the way that we use technology.
Yeah from each other and from God and from the creation right the creative world right it's just
this extent progress of further and further alienation than end.
And...
and atomization in that state is what it means to be a cursed.
Mm. Yeah.
Yeah. Yep. Yep. Well, on that depressing note,
we're going to take another short break and we'll be right back.
Stay with us, folks.
Damn it, and Father Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237.
7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Big in Heaven.
A collection of short stories available now
on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking,
sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox
or guarantee to shake your assumption.
and make you see your life and faith in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart,
but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Russ Gowr for help,
cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out.
Any work in the church, the woman was a styled,
a tallodish, you could count on.
No one knew her suffering.
They never bothered to look into our eyes.
It surprised me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander the world English parish didn't even know her name
It wasn't anything they thought about
To find this book another's like it you can go to store.AncientFaith.com
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen to Young
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
See, that commercial was not for one of my books, Father.
Does that make you happy?
It does.
We're sharing the love.
There we go.
Yeah, it's a lovely set of short stories, actually.
It's great.
It's good stuff.
Good stuff.
We endorse it.
See what I-
We blessed you, Beth.
We blessed the work of Father Stephen Ceneyari.
So, all right, well, welcome back.
We talked about blessings in our first half
and curses and cursing in our second half, especially.
And now in the third half of the show,
because once again, this is a show and a half.
We're going to talk about what it means to become a curse.
Everybody remember that language from Scripture?
want to talk about our Lord Jesus Christ be
a curse for us. So what does that mean in light of everything that else that we just said?
Well, it's a long story. So settle in everybody. Yeah.
Get yourself another cup of something. We always give listeners their value for the dollar
at least in terms of quantity, if not quality.
Yeah, so we're going to be talking now about the atonement again as is my want in particular,
but is as we've done on the show before but coming at it from sort of this perspective.
I was suddenly reminded that meme we've seen in our Facebook group that says,
I am once again asking to read Father Stevens' dissertation.
Yes, which is now available on ProQuest.
So there you are everybody.
access to the ProQuest dissertation database you can find it on.
there now. And I think it is literally because the Ambridge University Library was getting
requests for people and they got sick of it. So they, uh, good job. Very, very, very. Shout out to
Karen Sheridan Library in there for doing that for everybody. So I don't know if he listens, but
But so it turns up atonement and why
coming back there. In understanding the death of Christ and the way that
curse language is used there, we have to approach it home and ask the question,
what is the problem that's being dealt with here? So a lot of our friends in the
West will say that the problem that's being dealt with here is God's justice,
Right requires him to punish them.
Or...
God's wrath against sin has to be a piece or some variation of that.
There's all kinds of nuances on that.
But I would submit that if we're approaching this from the perspective of especially the
Old Testament and the Torah, what is the problem that is set up by the Hebrew Bible, by the
Old Testament that is going to be solved by Christ in the New Testament?
That problem comes down to curse, right?
the curse and impurity in the
two senses we talked about, right?
But with obviously what we call moral impurity being the
paradigmatic one because if you take care of that,
taking care of the rest of it is the ceremonial parts
relatively easy, right?
Yeah, right.
Because it results from the latter results from the former, right?
So the state occurs, the state of corruption within the
whole created order has to be dealt with.
Right.
And so we see in the Torah, the covenant
That's fine.
right, the covenant with Moses.
This entire system of sacrifice at the day of atonement,
of all these things, is set up to manage curse,
to manage this curse that infects,
and this rot that comes into this,
why mildew and stuff are used as sort of object lessons for it.
Right.
Yeah, I mean, it's one of those things.
It's like, yeah, there's commandment to the Torah
So, we're up.
for dealing with mildew and destroying walls
that have been infected with mold.
And I was reading that one time, I was like,
what is this about?
Why does God care about?
I mean, I just did it.
God cares about everything.
But it seems like a weird thing to kind of point out.
But as you said, it's about the sort of infection
and corruption and all that kind of thing.
And 11, how it gets into everything.
Yeah, active yeast cultures.
So bye.
This keeps coming up, right?
You keep offering the sacrifices,
but people keep committing sin, right?
And every year then on top of that,
you have to do the day of atonement, right?
And you're just constantly managing the situation
so that God won't have to leave
or God will break out,
His holiness will break out,
destroy the people, the camp or the nation.
Right?
And that's what ends up happening, of course.
It's like trying to keep a house clean
when you've got small children living in it.
There you go.
See, I'm reaching out to a huge segment of our listership.
They're like, yes, that's what it's like.
So yeah.
But having curse properly manages not the same as being in a state of blessiness.
Right.
It's not the same as participating in the divine life.
Those aren't the same thing, right?
It's like managing a chronic...
having it well managed is not the same as being healthy.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And so, the, the, the, that covenant as, as St. Paul and as Hebrews are going to point out again and again,
was never really aimed at solving that problem.
It was aimed at managing that problem until the solution came.
Right.
So, when you look at the day of atonement, rich...
You've got the two goats, right?
And the first goat, which is identified as a goat for a zazel, right,
that goat becomes a curse, right?
It becomes a curse in the sense that that moral unqueenness,
that curse, that corruption that comes through the participation
with the demonic powers, right?
The sinful actions of the people.
It was all put on and in that goat and that goat carries it away, right?
Right? Any carries?
it back to a zazel where it came from, right, back to the demonic powers from which it came originally.
Yeah. Then the second goat, the goat for Yahweh, the blood, that blood is used to purify the
ceremonial uncleanness, the residue, right, the result of that sin on the physical objects within
of the tablet, the holy place and the most holy place.
All of that is that pure...
that sort of ceremony, unclean residue that came from that corruption and curse within the camp.
Yeah, and let's say everybody, if you're new to the podcast, maybe this is one of the first episodes you're listening to,
if you're interested in way more about everything we just said about the goats and so forth,
there is an episode we did called The Priest Shall Make Atonement,
which is all about the day of atonement.
And for you long time listeners, this isn't in
the episode where he first started saying Christ is both goats.
Yes.
So yes.
To sort of hypertext one of our episodes to another.
So I'll be hyperlinked.
So this is, this is the,
this curse language is particularly connected to the mode of Christ that.
Right.
the idea that Christ dies hanging on a tree,
that Christ is crucified in particular.
So all the way back in Deuteronomy,
where we started tonight's episode,
Deuteronomy 21, verse 23,
we're told that person is anyone who has hanged on a tree.
And then they do this in Joshua with the king of I.
They go and hang them on a tree, right?
And so that happened to you.
that brings a curse upon the person that sort of makes them a focus of the curse.
This was done to the king of I because he was the king of the city,
the head of a giant clan, who was responsible for this sort of corruption.
Hard to get more cursed than that.
Right, and so in Galatians 313
Paul then talks about sites of this verse that is talking about Christ's
mode of death. The Christ died in that particular way to take the curse upon
himself, Allah the First Goat. That goes for Zazel, right? So the sort of the
transport mechanism that takes taking out the trash as it were, right? Yes, and
then Christ then descends into Hades and returns it to sender, right? Yeah,
Exactly.
But also, right, this is why this idea of curse and the purification of curse and replacing
curse with blessedness, right, this idea of reorientation and reconciliation, right,
also gets brought out when the New Testament talks about the cross of Christ.
So John 12 verse 32 after Christ refers to being lifted up the way the serpent was lifted
up in the wilderness.
Right, he says this is very...
famous line, and I, when I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all men to myself.
And everyone knew that he meant crucifixion, because they say, wait, wait, I thought,
what do you mean?
We were told that the Christ stays forever.
Yeah, so they know he's talking about his death.
They know he's talking about being crucified.
But the result is everybody is going to be drawn into a right relation.
gonna be drawn
to a right relationship with Christ and not all going to do it but they're going to be drawn to a
right relationship with Christ. Right and he's pointing to in the book of Numbers where the
Israelites are suffering from the venom of the serpent's right which is killing them
and the way they were purified from that was by looking upward to the image of what was afflicting them.
So Christ becomes a curse.
comes the image of what he's purifying us, but that's
done 12 verse 31. Christ points to that. And then the result
of that in verse 32 is this reconciliation, yeah, drawing all
men to himself. Cool, right. And St. Paul does the same move
in Romans 5 verse 10. Yeah, yeah, and there's a little bit
more Pauline language, slightly more complicated. So just
Listen everybody.
For if while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his son, much more now that we are reconciled shall we be saved by his life.
Right.
And so, remember that reconciliation is the same kind of idea St. Paul has been using throughout these early chapters of Romans, the one who is justified, the one who is blessed.
Right, record-style to God no longer alien.
right? Reoriented, redirected this blessed state, right? That's happened through the death of Christ. And now being reconciled, right?
Salvation and life come, right? The positive part. Salvation and life come through the blessed state.
Now that you're sort of plugged back in like you should be, you can then receive what you should be receiving by virtue of that communion with God.
And so then that's, you know, got one, right?
And goat number two, right?
To go for Yahweh, that blood is taken
and that blood is used, then as we said,
to sort of purify a way this curse, right?
The curse is wiped out by the blood.
And so this is talked about in different ways in scripture,
but you know, this blood thing
is counterintuitive to us, right?
I've said before I'm close.
when I go in bless houses, I don't have to go in there and throw sheep one all over.
I think I get fewer invitations to bless houses if I did.
And I don't think they think their house was particularly pure and clean after I was done,
either. Definitely would smell that way.
But there's some places where this is talked about.
One important one is in Hebrews 12 verse 24,
which is, yeah, which is talking about actually the date.
blood on the day of Atonement.
Yeah, yeah.
So then it continues on a previous sentence,
but this is the next clause.
To Jesus, the mediator of a new covenant
and to the sprinkled blood that speaks a better word
than the blood of Abel.
And Abel's blood, shed by cane,
is there in the ground crying out for justice?
Right.
crying out for the
the restoration. And so his blood being there in the ground and not in his body and him being murdered is an emblem of the curse. Right.
Yeah. Blood in the ground is the ground is not the way it should be.
And there's there's some weird icons of this. Right. There's these weird icons where you see.
I think it's where where Kane is speaking to God after this and you see what looks like a little man a little naked
man on the ground who is all red with his hands lifted up and that's Abel's blood
calling out to God from the ground for justice. So that's sort of the way that
that's sort of depicted iconographically. It's very strange, very very strange, but
it does exist in some icons. Yes.
So, and the parallel then is that it was sort of the emblem of the curves.
right of what is wrong, where is Christ blood purifies,
and restores, and deals with the curse.
Right.
Yeah.
Therefore, being better.
Right.
And so as we talked about in the pre-shell make
a tonement episode, Afro mentioned the killing
and ex-sanguination of goat number two
are not ritualized.
Right.
We're not told how they killed, how the blood was extracted
Exactly.
just that it was done.
And that means,
what something isn't ritualized,
that means it's not important
to the meaning of the ritual.
Yeah.
So what's important is what is done with the blood, right?
It's about the blood.
In order to get the blood of the animal,
you have to kill it,
and you have to remove the blood,
drain the blood.
But those are non-ritualized,
just sort of precursors.
Yeah. So do that.
There's not specific prayers that go with it or yeah.
Yeah.
So
So the very brief version, the very short version of how this works is that we're told
several places in the Torah that the blood of a person or an animal is their life.
And so it's life stuff.
And we just talked about curse, how curse is corruption and death stuff.
So you use light stuff together.
death stuff, to purify from death stuff. And as it talks about in Hebrews, it compares like the blood of
bulls and goats to the blood of Christ, right? Christ being God, his life is eternal. It's the life of God
himself. Right. Which is both. It was, which why I has a much bigger effect, not just bigger, a very
different effect than simply with animals.
The blood of an animal, right?
There's no comparison, right?
Yeah, right.
And so Christ's blood is therefore his death
and that his blood are able to do this once and for all,
solve the problem, not just continue managing it.
But this identification of blood as life is also, of course,
why, and I think we've talked about this before on the show,
too, there are all these strict prohibitions
against the drinking of blood.
Right.
And the eating of animals with the blood still in them
the Old Testament and continued in the New Testament, right? It's like sexual immorality,
idolatry and eating and drinking blood that the Gentile Christians are not allowed to do.
And so the reason for that is that you are making very direct and very clear and acting out
life feeding on life.
Right.
Life feeding on life.
And the scriptures are putting forward another paradigm which is life destroying that.
Right.
Which is pointing us to Christ whose life destroys that.
Which is why the Eucharist in which we drink the blood of Christ does not violate this
prohibition against the drinking of blood because it's not life feeding on life.
it's life destroying death. We are the ones who are deathly and and it's Christ's life destroying
death in us. It's not us feeding ourselves with the blood of an animal. Right? So so you have to
understand this a little bit more deeply and you can't just say, where else was it drinking blood?
You know, how can you have the Eucharist? Again, remember, the Lord Himself gives it. He says,
this is my blood, right? So we had to try to understand why he would
say that and that he's not violating the Torah. He's actually revealing what the Torah was kind of
always about. There was always pointing ultimately to this, you know, that the Eucharist is
among other things a kind of, I don't know, if inversion or subversion or reversal, I'm not sure
which word we should use, but it's not the same thing because, as you said, it's Christ's life is in
in that blood, which is a different kind of life than
created life. God's own life. Right, exactly. Exactly. And it's why, you know, you don't eat and drink the
sacrifices of demons because then you're feeding on demons. And they destroy you. You're
into Kino Nio with demons. Exactly. I mean, literally, yeah, literally the word that St. Paul uses, I
don't want you to have Kino Nio with demons. You know, you only have that with God. And we do that in
and Christ, do we do that?
in this life most intensely in the Eucharist.
So yeah, yeah.
So pen ultimately by way of summary,
we wanted to take a quick stroll through Psalm 1.
Very go.
Which as we mentioned earlier,
starts out with the word at least in the Greek Psalms,
Maccadios, Maccadios, Anir.
Blessed is the man.
Yeah, and...
So I think we'll see here summarized a lot of the things that we've been talking about today.
Yeah, pretty cool.
Okay, we're going to take this first by verse.
So we're going to break it down.
Straight out J.
We're going to begin it.
He only took him five years to get through the bubble.
I may finish by the end of this calendar year.
It is not impossible.
Really?
12 and a half.
you know all these people are gonna be ready for course
If you finish it by the end of this calendar year, it's going to be what next June or July
before the podcast will.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Just tantalizing.
Just be patient.
People be patient.
Yeah.
So okay, someone.
First one.
Blessed is the man who walks not in the council of the wicked, nor stands in the way of sinners,
nor sits in the seat of scoffers.
So we've talked about that word blessed a lot, right?
That it's this.
And of course, in this case, it's not of loyitos.
It's macadios in the Greek that that blissfulness,
life of the blissfulness of the gods, right?
You know, so we've covered blessedness.
So what about the rest of this verse?
Like how does that fit into this?
Well, you know, there's the emphasis on walking,
which means this is a way of life, right?
This is not.
if you do this God.
will give you a blessing. Yeah, it's not about accomplished deeds. It's about way of living.
Right. The person who lives in this way will be in this state of blessedness, right? That that will be
and you see that in this case the state of curse just like the state of blessedness is sort of
communal, right? Because it's about sharing in the council of the wicked way of sinners, the seat of
of scoppers, right? This is about...
having Ketania about having communion with the wicked, which is what the
blessed man does not do. He is therefore correctly oriented as opposed to these
others who are not. Yeah, so that's verse 1. Okay, all right. So verse 2, but, so this
is in contrast, but his delight is in the law of the Lord, and on his law he
meditates.
day and night. So law there, right? That's the Torah. That's the commandments of God.
He grew, he grew it's literally the word Torah. Yeah. So his delight is on the Torah of the Lord,
and on his Torah he meditates day and night. So basically it's a biblical scholar, huh?
Yes, that's what it's saying. Just throwing that out there. We should all be on some level.
Just the Torah though. Right. Right.
Yeah, yeah, we have to read this one of those things.
always translated law even in an Old Testament verse like this but it's literally the word Torah
right which includes Genesis and which includes all the narrative parts of the Torah
so if someone wants to make a distinction between the Torah and the law like the two different things
you're going to first have to tell me what Hebrew word you're referring to as law
and where I would find that because here it's about the Torah right which means teaching
as we've said before, right? Yeah. So rather than sharing this communion with the wicked,
right, he focuses on the commandments which have life in them, right, in the Torah. And this is his
focus, right? And so he is living his life in his way and acting in a way of good order which is
she's going to bring forth life.
What might you even say, life and that abundance?
Yeah, yeah, I mean, I love how we're the word I don't know what it is in the Greek or the Hebrew,
but the word delight his delight is in the law of the Lord like there's this
it's not you know, it's funny following the following laws we don't tend to think of it as delightful.
It's so delightful to drive the speed limit. It's so like we don't think of it that way right, but but it
is described as delight here because it's not just about obeying
things that are in a law book.
It's, yeah.
It's this whole blessed way of life. Okay, so verse three
He is like a tree. So again, this is talking about the man who's blessed, right?
He is like a tree planted by streams of water that yields its fruit in its season
and its leaf does not wither. In all that he does, he prospers.
So, you know, again, this is not... Now this is not a...
This is not prosperity gospel.
There it is. There it is.
I'm not a professional.
God is good all the time.
Notice the chicken and the egg thing here.
He's like a tree.
But notice the tree is planted in a particular place.
Right.
So it's not just a question of wow he's a really great tree.
Because if you put the really great tree in a desert,
it would not yield its fruit and it's easy.
And it's leafwood wither.
So there is a question.
a question of a system of relationships here,
being in a certain orientation,
being connected and in harmony with the rest of,
right, that the creator order around him.
So that he yields the fruit,
and so that, again, you have the unwhithering leaf,
right, this idea of eternal life, right, ongoing life,
right, and it's so that because of that
bringing forth of life, there is this prosperity, right?
but that prosperity is it again.
The tree isn't collecting a lot of stuff.
Yeah, it's yielding fruit.
The tree is successfully being a good tree.
Yeah, growing tall and strong and producing fruit, right?
Like we talked about with the good chair and the bad chair, right?
Like it's fulfilling, he's fulfilling his purpose for which he was created.
Right. Right.
And, and you know, I mean, thus this, this lights up statements like you
you shall know a tree by its fruit.
You can know that it's being a good tree.
because it produces the good fruit. Okay, so verse 4, the wicked are not so, but are like
chaff that the wind drives away. So this is now talking about the curse, right? This is the
cursed way of being. And it's interesting, it's not just that they're like dead stuff for whatever,
It's, it's chaff, which is, which is garbage and it's very nature, right?
You know, I wanted it all.
It can't be fixed. It's just bad.
And it's been cut out, right?
It's been cut off from the ground, right?
It's been cut off from the fruit it was supposed to bear.
Yeah, it's the garbage part.
It's the useless part, but it's been severed from everything and it's dead.
Yeah, and there's this alien in cut off everything.
Threshing going on that makes the chaff blown away in the wind.
Right. And the wind blows and it's gone because it's not connected to anything.
Hmm.
It's not substantial.
Yeah.
Okay, verse 5, we're getting close to wrapping up the Psalm here.
Therefore, the wicked will not stand in the judgment, nor sinners in the congregation of the righteous.
So this is interesting because this is talking about that context of the communal life,
And this is it uses a couple of different images the judgment the congregation of the right to
I mean, this is the divine counsel, right?
That comes together, they're assembled,
they're presided over by the Lord,
and they render judgment,
meaning they put things in order, right?
Because I remember everybody,
that's what justice is being put in order.
They render judgment, it's the congregation of the righteous.
These are the people who are in tune with God,
who are doing his will, who are being obedient to him.
And this verse says that the wicked are not there,
that centers are not there.
Right. They're the blessed community that's blessing and being blessed, that's sharing this
participation in this community, this Kenania with each other and with God.
Right. And the sinner, the wicked have cut themselves off from that.
They have alienated themselves from that and not been reconciled.
Alright, well the final verse, verse 6, I think probably some...
people as they listen to this, they remember that this is sometimes used as a communion
hymn, right?
Blessed is the man.
Isn't it also used, I think, in a festival of great vespers towards the beginning?
Yeah.
Okay.
So verse 6, for the Lord knows the way of the righteous, but the way of the wicked will perish.
I'm if this is there on the way, right?
And so it...
It's the way of being in the world, the way of life, the way of living, right?
The inner yeah, the, right, of these two groups, right?
I notice it's not two individuals.
It's two groups, two communities, two communities, right?
One has one way, the other one has another way, right?
and the path
the way of the righteous, right?
The Lord is part of that.
That's why he knows it.
Right.
He is a part of it, right?
Yes, that knowledge of experience
and communion together.
Right, and so the wicked have cut themselves off
from that again, right?
And so it's just, it's curse, it's just corruption.
It has no substance.
And so it just gets wiped away.
Cool. Alright, well, some closing thoughts. I think we might have mentioned this, I know
that you certainly have in other places, Father, but I think we've mentioned this on the
podcast before, but I just wanted to underline it, especially in light of this episode about
blessing and curses, which is, you know, this last word that we mentioned that has to do
with blessing, Maccadios, which is this description of the blissfulness of, you know, in pagan
religion is the blissfulness of the gods with their
most Thai God, but it's used in the Bible to refer to this way that the angels and saints
are with the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. And this gets used in the Beatitudes, right? Where
Christ gives this sermon, blessed are the poor and Spirit, blessed are the meek, blessed are,
you know, and there's a series of blessed. And again, it's not the word of Loiitos,
which...
Again, it's related to Evelot, it's from Evelogia, right?
This endorsement are the good word.
So it's not wrong, right?
That wouldn't be wrong.
But it does specifically use macadios, which
is this word that refers to this communion of gods with God.
OK?
So the be attitudes get used in a couple of places
that I think are important for us to just...
note. One is in a funeral. So in the Orthodox funeral service traditionally we sing the
piaotitudes. And you might wonder why, why is that being sung or read or however whatever
it is in a particular tradition, why is that there? It's because in the funeral service what
we are doing is commending, endorsing as it were, to God this person who has died,
And what we're specifically commending them to God for is this blissful divine life with
the righteous, this life as lowercase G gods who serve the most high God who is above
all gods, King of kings, Lord of lords, God of gods.
So it's speaking about handing them over to God and our prayers that they be received
into that life.
So we use the beatitudes in the funeral service for this purpose.
The other place that it shows up, and probably a lot of Orthodox Christians may not know this because their tradition doesn't always include it.
But especially for those who are more familiar with the Slavic liturgical tradition, but frankly, if you go to even in the Greek liturgical tradition, you go to a monastery, you'll hear this.
You'll hear this.
is the Beatitudes are used in the Antiphons at the beginning of the Divine Liturgy.
Right?
So again, it's not a normal part of life if you're at a Greek Orthodox parish or an Antiochian Orthodox parish,
some others normally, but it is included.
It is the traditional, one of the traditional hymns that's sung towards the beginning of the Liturgy.
If you go to church with a Russian tradition,
the liturgical life, you're gonna...
hear it all the time, you know. The the the the Beatitudes at the Lord speaks. And so why
is that in the divine liturgy? Why is that there? It's there because the divine liturgy, there's
a lot of things we could say about it. I'm going to say this thing. The divine liturgy is an entrance
into and a participation in that blissfulness, that divine happiness, that
that the angels and saints share with the Father,
Son and Holy Spirit,
that blessed righteous community and communion
that they participate in with each other.
That's what's going on there.
So when we participate in the divine liturgy,
we are entering into that life.
We are entering into,
there's a reason that the priest at the beginning
says, blessed is the kingdom of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit.
It's because we're entering into that kingdom of God
as we participate in.
that. Now that doesn't mean that all the other services the Church don't also do that if they don't
include the Beatitudes. But there's something particularly powerful about the way that the divine
liturgy does it that's kind of above everything else. And like I said within the scope of the funeral,
we're handing this person over in a sense to the eternal divine liturgy that is what life in the
kingdom of God and the age to come is about. Right. And I wanted to point that out because one of our
one of our goals with this
podcast is to always refer people back to actual life in the church. You know, because that's where
you actually do this stuff. You don't do it by listening to a podcast as fun as it might be.
You do it by participating in the life of the church, which means especially its liturgical life
and everything else that flows out of that. And I think to point out that this blessedness,
as we described it. This blessedness is what is being sung about
particularly in those two contexts, but in so many others as well.
I think that it helps to light up our experience of a liturgical life.
That to me is one of the big experiences of all the things that I've learned
in the course of doing this podcast is it lights up the liturgical life for me.
It's see things everywhere that I didn't use to see.
It's such a delight, right?
And it draws you more deeply in.
So that's the stuff that I wanted to walk away with from this particular episode
and
And I think it's, again, I'm just astonished at the wonders and the richness and the depth
of the knowledge of God that's given to us in his body, the Church.
Father Stephen?
So in so far as I have a part in picking topics for the podcast that I had a part
picking this one. I often pick them based on things I'm currently thinking about. And in this case,
part of the reason for our topic tonight is that someone who is not a Christian asked in my presence,
semi rhetorically what does Christianity have to say about alienation?
specifically about sort of the alienation of modern contemporary life.
And as a non-Christian who's been exposed primarily to, and at a distance, to certain forms of Western Christianity,
The question kind of makes sense in the sense that
for a person like this, Christianity seems to be
Try to...
at least say for Christianity they would take seriously,
seems to be focused primarily on salvation aimed at
an afterlife.
The idea that Christianity is about what must I do
to be safe if I die tonight, where would I be,
where would I go?
And if you're thinking of that type of Christianity,
I don't know what that type of Christianity would have to say to someone who's feeling
alienated and alone and cut off in this world other than, hey, if you do XYZ, whether
it's prayer, whether it's joy, this particular church, or particular sacraments or whatever,
then you know, at least when you die, you'll have eternal bliss.
And it actually gets far worse if you go down the
road of our universalist friends, because that really lets you off the hook, right?
Because hey, starving children, well, don't worry, you know, turn it, you've litelates
them.
Everyone else in the world.
So all this stuff becomes super relative, right?
You don't even have to do XYZ, necessarily.
And then on the other side, in certain segments of modern Christianity.
and rebelling against that. They go in the opposite direction where they don't talk about that at all.
They might not even believe that that even exists, that death is just it.
And so you have sort of vague social concern.
And to be honest, history, not a social concern that's produced much actual good in the world at that.
And it's really done anything to fight people sense of alienation and loneliness and being cut off.
So, you know, sort of what's the answer then.
And another weird habit I've developed for years now is I read Nietzsche during Lent.
And it's helpful because it kind of beats up your intellect if you listen to it amongst other things.
But there's one place where Nietzsche talks about what's been called.
by people who interpret him, the idea of the eternal return,
which is where he says, you know, what would happen if at your darkest moment in life,
a demon came to you and told you that essentially all of this has happened before
and all of this will happen again.
Right? And in an infinite timeline, everything that can happen will happen
happen and the infinite number of times.
And so the idea of being need you to say,
the life you live now, you live over and over and over again.
Every bad part, every good part.
But then he asked the question, what would that do in terms of how you live your life?
And so I don't agree with each of the bets how it works, obviously.
I don't even know if each I agree with each of the bets how it really works.
But the idea that eternal life, the eternal life that is talked about...
and scripture, and you can especially see this in St. John's Gospel.
It begins now and is shaped by now.
And it has its model in the life we live now.
I think Nietzsche unintentionally gives us kind of a way into that.
That eternal life, that eternal life, that life of bliss, that blessed life,
is not.
something that awaits us in a future if we keep the rules or do the right things now.
It's something that has the potential to begin now.
It's a life that can begin to burst forth now and then continue into eternity.
And so I think what Christianity, what real Christianity has to say
to the alienated person is that now today is the beginning.
of the time to be reconciled, not just to be reconciled to God through some kind of religious
procedure, but to be reconciled to God by being reconciled to your neighbor, by to your
literal neighbor, to your friends, to your family, to your community, to the world itself,
and then through reconciliation to those things, to become truly reconciled to God, and through
being reconciled to come to particip.
in his life as we read St Paul speaking about in Romans 5 and this is it again an
esoteric idea right this begins with picking up a phone and calling someone we
haven't talked to in years and saying you know what the last time we talked
that was a jerk and I'm sorry and I want to fix it and I know it's weird that I'm
calling you after all these years.
but I don't like how we left it.
Or calling the person who you just haven't talked to in years
who you have a sneaking suspicion might just need to talk
to something.
Or talking to the person you see every day and don't talk to.
Beginning to fix those things, very simple things
that any one of us can do because they don't cost any money.
They cost us very little time.
And we have more than enough of that
that we're wasting on technology and trying
to satisfy our desires.
but those little steps that be...
to lead to something that is beautiful and blessed and
last forever. So those are my concluding thoughts.
Thank you. Well that is our show for today. Thank you for
listening everyone. If you didn't get through to us live we'd
still love to hear from you. You can email us at LordOfSpiritz
at AncientFaith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordOfSpiritz.
and join us for a
live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.s.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific, which Lord willing will actually be live for a while now.
Hey man, if you're on Facebook, like our page, join our discussion group,
leave reviews and readings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend
that you know or suspect is going to love it. And finally be sure to go to
www.inxupate.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
our broadcasters stay on the air.
Thank you.
Good night, God bless you.
Christ is risen.
He truly is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener.
of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
versus 11 through 12.